這是關於你的故事
This is a story about you
也關於我和你的狗
and me and your dog.
不久之前  在狗出現之前
There was a time not long ago... before dogs.
他們以前不存在
They didn't exist.
現在的狗有大有小 寵物狗
Now there are big ones, small ones, snugglers,
守護犬  獵犬
guardians, hunters.
各式各樣的狗
Every kind of dog you could possibly want.
怎麼會這樣
How did that happen?
不僅僅是狗
It's not just dogs.
形形色色的各種生物
Where did all the different kinds
都是從哪裏來的呢
of living creatures come from?
答案是來自能量的轉換  聽上去可能
The answer is a transforming power that sounds like something
像是童話或者神話
straight out of a fairy tale or myth,
但並非如此
but it's no such thing.
中文翻譯 @SaltyEggPain timhal
Bluray版字幕  timhal@HDWinG字幕組
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息
宇宙大探索
第二集
讓我們回到3萬年前 狗狗誕生前
Let's go back across 30,000 years to a time before dogs,
那是我們的祖先生活在最後一次冰河時代的無盡冬夜
when our ancestors lived in the endless winter of the last ice age.
我們的祖先小規模的群居 遊蕩著
Our ancestors were wanderers living in small bands.
他們睡在星空下
They slept beneath the stars.
星星就是他們的故事書  日曆
The sky was their storybook, calendar,
生活指南
an instruction manual for living.
星星告訴他們嚴寒何時到來
It told them when the bitter colds would come,
穀物何時成熟
when the wild grains would ripen,
鹿群和野牛群何時遷徙
when the herds of caribou and bison would be on the move.
他們對家的印象就是地球本身
Their idea of home was Earth itself.
但是他們受到其他飢餓生物的威脅
But they lived in fear of other hungry creatures...
比如獅子和熊
the mountain lions and the bears
與他們搶奪同樣地獵物
that competed with them for the same prey
還有狼群會掠食他們中
and the wolves that threatened to carry off and devour
最脆弱的同伴
the most vulnerable among them.
所有的狼都想來分一杯羹
All the wolves want to get at the bone,
但大部分都不敢靠的太近
but most of them are too frightened to come close enough.
他們的恐懼來自血液中
Their fear is due to high levels
高濃度的應激激素
of stress hormones in their blood.
這是生死攸關的問題
It's a matter of survival.
因為靠的太近可能很致命
Because coming too close to humans can be fatal.
但也有些狼  因為自然差異
But a few wolves-- due to natural variations--
這種激素濃度較低
have lower levels of those hormones.
使得他們不是那麼懼怕人類
This makes them less afraid of humans.
這頭狼和他祖先
This wolf has discovered
中的一個分支發現了同樣的情況
what a branch of his ancestors figured out
大約在1萬5千年前
some 15,000 years ago...
一個完美的生存策略
an excellent survival strategy;
人類的馴化
the domestication of humans.
在人類捕獵時別威脅到他們
Let the humans do the hunting, don't threaten them,
他們會允許你以殘渣為食
and they'll let you scavenge their garbage.
你吃的更規律 就可以繁衍更多的後代
You'll eat more regularly, you'll leave more offspring,
這些後代會繼承你的性情
and those offspring will inherit your disposition.
這種馴養的淘汰方式
This selection for tameness
效果逐代加強
would be reinforced with each generation
直到這一系的野狼進化為
until that line of wild wolves evolves into...
狗
dogs.
你可以稱它為最友善的生存
You might call this "survival of the friendliest."
現在看來 這也是對人類非常有利的
Then as now, this was a good deal for the humans, too.
那些吃剩飯的狗並不只是收拾垃圾
The scavenging dogs weren't just a sanitation squad.
他們也是保安力量
They worked security.
隨著這種不同物種間的合作
As this interspecies partnership continued over time,
狗的外貌也發生了改變
the dogs' appearance changed also.
可愛變成了優勝劣汰時的優勢
Cuteness became a selective advantage.
你越可愛 就有更大的機會活下去
The more adorable you were, the better chance you had
並把你的基因傳遞給下一代
to live and pass on your genes to another generation.
起先是為了便利而結成的聯盟
What began as an alliance of convenience
變成了越來越深厚的友誼
became a friendship that deepened over time.
接下來發生了什麼
To see what happens next,
我們略過2萬年前的先祖
let's leave our distant ancestors
看看不是很久以前的古人
of some 20,000 years ago to visit the more recent past
在冰河時代的間歇期
during an intermission in the Ice Age.
平和的氣候帶來了一場變革
This break in the climate starts a revolution.
人類不再流浪  而是定居下來
Instead of wandering, people are settling down.
新的事物出現了  村莊
There's something new in the world... villages.
人們依然在打獵和採集食物
People still hunt and gather,
但也開始了製造食物和衣服
but now they also produce food and clothing...
農業
agriculture.
狼用他們的自由
The wolves have traded their freedom
來交換穩定的食物供應
in exchange for a steady meal.
他們放棄了選擇夥伴的權利
They've given up their right to choose a mate.
人類替他們選擇
Now the humans choose for them.
他們消滅無法被馴服的狗
They consistently kill off the dogs that can't be trained;
那些會咬人的狗
the ones that bite the feeding hand.
他們繁育那些討喜的狗
And they breed the dogs that please them.
讓這些狗服從命令
They nurture those dogs that do their bidding...
打獵  放牧  守衛  拖拽重物
hunting, herding, guarding, hauling,
陪伴人類
and keeping them company.
從每一窩小狗中
From every litter,
選擇那些他們最喜歡的
the humans select the puppies they like best.
一代接一代 狗進化了
Over the generations, the dogs evolve.
稱之為 人工選擇
This kind of evolution is called "artificial selection"
或者  飼養
or "breeding."
把狼變成狗 是人類第一次
Turning wolves into dogs was the first time
親手干預進化過程
we humans took evolution into our own hands.
從那以後我們改進了
And we've been doing it ever since
對我們有用的植物和動物
to shape all the plants and animals that we depend on.
彈指一揮間 大約1萬5千到2萬年裏
In a blink of cosmic time, just 15,000 or 20,000 years,
我們把灰狼改變成為了
we turned gray wolves into all the kinds of dogs
各種各樣的可愛的狗
we love today.
想想看
Think of it.
各個品種的狗
Every breed of dog you've ever seen
都是人類塑造出來的
was sculpted by human hands.
其中大部分 最受歡迎的品種
Many of our best friends-- the most popular breeds--
都是最近幾百年培育出來的
were created in only the last few centuries.
進化的強大力量
The awesome power of evolution
將窮兇極惡的狼
transformed the ravenous wolf
變成忠心耿耿的牧羊犬
into the faithful shepherd...
保護 看守羊群 並驅趕狼群
...who protects the herd and drives the wolf away.
人工培育 把狼變成狗
Artificial selection turned the wolf into the shepherd
把野草變成小麥和玉米
and the wild grasses into wheat and corn.
事實上 大部分我們食用的植物和動物
In fact, almost every plant and animal that we eat today
都是來自野生的 不可食用的品種
was bred from a wild, less-edible ancestor.
如果強大的人工選擇可以在1萬到1萬5千年間
If artificial selection can work such profound changes
帶來如此巨大的變化
in only 10,000 or 15,000 years,
那麼大自然的選擇淘汰
what can natural selection do
在上百萬年間可以做到怎樣的程度呢
operating over billions of years?
形形色色美好的生命就是答案
The answer is all the beauty and diversity of life.
怎麼做到得
How does it work?
我們的想像之舟可以帶我們去任何地方
Our Ship of the Imagination can take us anywhere in space
任何時間 甚至看不見的小宇宙
and time, even to the hidden microcosmos,
在哪裏 生命可以完成蛻變
where one kind of life can be transformed into another.
跟我來
Come with me.
看上去可能不像
May not seem like it,
我們曾經生活在冰河時期
but we've been living in an ice age
長達2百萬年之久
for the last two million years.
現在只是其中一個間歇期
This just happens to be one of the long intermissions.
2百萬年間的大部分時期
For most of those two million years,
氣候又冷又干
the climate has been cold and dry.
北極冰蓋比今天
The North Polar ice cap extended much farther south
所看到的範圍更大
than it does today.
在這漫長的冰川期
In one of those long, cold glacial periods
從北極來的冬季海水冰
when the winter sea ice stretched from the North Pole
一直延伸至今日洛杉磯所在的位置
all the way down to what is now Los Angeles,
大灰熊在冰凍荒蕪的愛爾蘭遊蕩
great bears roamed the frozen wastes of Ireland.
這頭熊看上去很普通
This might look like an ordinary bear,
但是她的內在卻有著不平凡的變化
but something extraordinary is happening inside her.
一股催生新物種的力量
Something that will give rise to a new species.
要探究這股力量
In order to see it,
我們要把比例尺調整到
we'll need to descend down to a much smaller scale,
細胞級別
to the cellular level,
這樣才能探究熊的生殖系統
so that we can explore the bear's reproductive system.
我們通過鎖骨下的動脈穿過心臟
We'll take the subclavian artery through the heart.
快到了
Almost there.
那是一些她的卵子
Those are some of her eggs.
要想瞭解這些卵子的詳情
To see what's going on in one of them,
我們必須變得更小
we'll have to get even smaller.
縮小到分子級別
We'll have to shrink down to the molecular level.
我們的想像之舟有多小呢
Our Ship of the Imagination is now so small,
只有一顆沙粒的百萬分之一
you could fit a million of them into a grain of sand.
看到那些闊步前進的小傢伙嗎
See those guys over there strutting along those girders?
他們是蛋白質 叫做驅動蛋白
They are proteins called kinesin.
這些驅動蛋白是搬運工
These kinesin are part of the transport crew
忙碌地在細胞間傳遞貨物
that's busy moving cargo around the cell.
長得就像外星人
How alien they seem.
他們和其他長相類似的小傢伙
And yet these tiny creatures-- and beings like them--
存在於每個活細胞中 包括我們的細胞
are a part of every living cell, including the ones inside you.
如果生命體也有聖殿
If life has a sanctuary,
那就是細胞核 包含了我們的
it's here in the nucleus which contains our DNA...
我們遺傳密碼的遠古聖經
the ancient scripture of our genetic code.
由所有生命體都能理解的語言寫成
And it's written in a language that all life can read.
DNA是一種長螺旋階梯狀的分子
DNA is a molecule shaped like a long twisted ladder
也叫雙螺旋結構
or double helix.
階梯的橫檔是由4種
The rungs of the ladder are made
不同的小分子組成
of four different kinds of smaller molecules.
這些就是基因字母表中的字母
These are the letters of the genetic alphabet.
這些字母的特定排列組合
Particular arrangements of those letters spell out
產生出針對所有生命體的指令
the instructions for all living things,
告訴他們如果生長 移動 消化
telling them how to grow, move, digest,
感知環境 癒合 繁殖
sense the environment, heal, reproduce.
DNA雙螺旋就是一台分子機器
The DNA double helix is a molecular machine
由1千億稱之為原子的部件組成
with about 100 billion parts called "atoms."
單個DNA分子中的原子數量
There are as many atoms in a single molecule of your DNA
多的就像銀河系中的繁星數量
as there are stars in a typical galaxy.
和狗一樣
The same is true for dogs
和熊一樣
and bears
和所有生物一樣
and every living thing.
我們 每一個人 就是一個小宇宙
We are, each of us, a little universe.
DNA信息在細胞與細胞間
The DNA message handed down from cell to cell
也在一代接一代的繁衍中異常謹慎地複製著
and from generation to generation is copied with extreme care.
當一條鬆開的蛋白質分開雙螺旋的兩條邊
The birth of a new DNA molecule begins when an unwinding protein
拆開中間的橫檔
separates the two strands of the double helix,
新的DNA分子就誕生了
breaking the rungs apart.
細胞核的液體中
Inside the liquid of the nucleus,
遺傳密碼的分子字母自由的游動
the molecular letters of the genetic code float freely.
雙螺旋的其中一邊複製著失去的另外一邊
Each strand of the helix copies its lost partner,
變成兩個完全一樣的DNA分子
resulting in two identical DNA molecules.
這就是生命體如果繁衍和傳遞基因
That's how life reproduces genes and transmits them
代代相傳
from one generation to the next.
當一個活細胞分裂成兩個
When a living cell divides in two,
每個細胞都帶有一份完整的
each one takes away with it a complete copy of the DNA.
一種特定的蛋白質負責校對
A specialized protein proofreads to make sure
確保只接受正確的字母
that only the right letters are accepted
這保證了DNA的準確複製
so that the DNA is accurately copied.
但是沒有什麼是完美的
But nobody's perfect.
偶爾 校對也會發生失誤
Occasionally, a proofreading error slips through,
在遺傳指令中產生了細微的隨機變化
making a small, random change in the genetic instructions.
這頭熊的卵子細胞中發生了突變
A mutation has occurred in the bear's egg cell.
如此細微的隨機事件也會帶來
A random event as tiny as this one can have consequences
很大的影響
on a far grander scale.
突變改變了控制毛皮顏色的基因
That mutation altered the gene that controls fur color.
它影響了這只熊的後代的深色毛皮的產生
It will affect the production of dark pigment in the fur
of the bear's offspring.
大多數突變是無害的
Most mutations are harmless.
有些是致命的
Some are deadly.
少數 純屬偶然 使得某個生物
But a few, purely by chance, can give an organism
在競爭中獲得重大優勢
a critical advantage over the competition.
1年後
A year has passed.
這只熊做了母親
Our bear is now a mother.
作為突變的結果
And as a result of that mutation,
其中一隻熊寶寶生來就是白色的皮毛
one of her two cubs was born with a white coat.
當兩隻熊長大到可以自己獵食時
When the cubs get old enough to venture out on their own,
哪頭熊更可能
which bear is more likely
悄悄地接近他們的獵物
to be able to sneak up on unsuspecting prey?
棕熊和雪區別明顯  很遠就能被察覺
The brown bear can be seen against the snow a mile away.
白熊子孫滿堂 並把他獨特的基因
The white bear prospers and passes on
傳遞下去
its own particular set of genes.
這樣的情況不斷發生
This happens repeatedly.
再接下去的幾代裏
Over succeeding generations,
白色皮毛的基因散播遍及整個北極的熊
the gene for white fur spreads through the entire population of Arctic bears.
深色皮毛的基因消亡在
The gene for dark fur loses out
生存的競爭中
in the competition for survival.
突變是完全隨機並且時刻發生的
Mutations are entirely random and happen all the time.
但是環境會對獎勵那些
But the environment rewards those
對生存有利的突變
that increase the chance for survival.
大自然選擇那些可以更好適應環境的生物
It naturally selects the living things that are better suited to survive.
這種選擇絕對不是隨機的
And that selection is the opposite of random.
兩個種群的熊各自分開
The two populations of bears separated,
經過了上千年
and over thousands of years,
進化出各自獨有的特徵
evolved other characteristics that set them apart.
他們變成了不同的物種
They became different species.
這就是查爾斯 達爾文所說的
That's what Charles Darwin meant
物種起源
by "the origin of species."
單個的熊不會進化
An individual bear doesn't evolve;
一群熊在幾代繁衍中進化
the population of bears evolves over generations.
如果北極的冰日益減少
If the Arctic ice continues to dwindle
全球變暖的緣故 北極熊可能滅絕
due to global warming, the polar bears may go extinct.
他們會被棕熊取代
They'll be replaced by brown bears,
可以更好地適應冰融後的環境
better adapted to the now defrosted environment.
這個故事和狗的進化不一樣
This is a different story from the one about the dogs.
沒有人去指導這個變化
No breeder guided these changes.
他們都是由自然環境選擇的
Instead, the environment itself selects them.
這就是物競天擇
This is evolution by natural selection,
科學歷史上最顛覆性的理論
the most revolutionary concept in the history of science.
1859年 達爾文首次提出了支持這個理論的證據
Darwin first presented the evidence for this idea in 1859.
它帶來的爭議從未消退
The uproar it caused has never subsided.
為什麼
Why?
我們都可以理解那種令人不適的刺痛
We all understand the twinge of discomfort
我們是由猩猩進化而來的
at the thought that we share a common ancestor with the apes.
在我們的想法裏 親戚 最能讓我們感到丟臉
No one can embarrass you like a relative.
我們的近親  黑猩猩
Our closest ones, the chimpanzees,
他們頻繁在公共場合做出不當的舉止
they frequently behave inappropriately in public.
人類想和他們保持距離
There's an understandable human need
也是可以理解的
to distance ourselves from them.
傳統信仰的核心前提
A central premise of traditional belief
我們是造物者特製的
is that we were created separately
和其他動物有區別的
from all the other animals.
這種觀點也很容易被理解
It's easy to see why this idea has taken hold.
它讓我們覺得 與眾不同
It makes us feel... special.
如果我們和這些樹是親戚呢
But what about our kinship with the trees?
你又作何感想
How does that make you feel?
這是橡樹DNA的一部分
Okay, here's a segment of the oak tree's DNA.
把它看做條形碼
Think of it like a bar code.
生命代碼的指令
The instructions written in the code of life
告訴這個樹如何分解糖分
tell the tree how to metabolize sugar.
拿它和我自己的DNA作比較
Now let's compare it with the same section of my own DNA.
DNA不會撒謊
The DNA doesn't lie.
這棵樹就是我失散已久的表親
This tree and me-- we're long-lost cousins.
不單單是樹
And it's not just the trees.
如果回到很久以前 我們可以發現
If you go back far enough, you'll find that we share
我們有著共同的祖先
a common ancestor with...
蝴蝶
the butterfly...
灰狼
gray wolf...
蘑菇
mushroom...
鯊魚
shark...
細菌
bacterium...
麻雀
sparrow.
多麼幸福的一家人
What a family!
條形碼的其他部分因人而異
Other parts of the bar code vary from species to species.
這也使得貓頭鷹和章魚有所區別
That's what makes the difference between an owl and an octopus.
除非你有一個同卵雙胞胎
Unless you have an identical twin,
這個世界上不會有人
there's no one else in the universe
和你有著相同的
with the exact same DNA as you.
其他的物種中 遺傳基因的不同
Within other species, the genetic differences
為自然選擇提供了原材料
provide the raw material for natural selection.
環境決定了什麼基因可以生存繁衍
The environment selects which genes survive and multiply.
說到生物遺傳基因的指令中
When it comes to the genetic instructions for life's
最基本的功能
most basic functions--
比方說分解糖分  我們和其他物種
say, digesting sugars-- we and other species
幾乎一致
are almost identical.
因為這些是生命最基本的功能
That's because those functions are so basic to life,
他們在各種不同生命形式誕生前
they evolved before the various life-forms
就已經進化完成
branched off from each other.
這就是我們的生命之樹
This is our Tree of Life.
科學使我們可以
Science has made it possible
為地球上的所有生物
for us to construct this family tree
繪製這份家譜
for all the species of life on Earth.
相近基因的親戚住在同一根的枝幹上
Close genetic relatives occupy the same branch of the tree,
差異越大住得越遠
while more distant cousins are farther away.
每根細枝都是一個物種
Each twig is a living species.
主桿代表著地球上所有生命的
And the trunk of the tree represents the common ancestors
共同祖先
of all life on Earth.
生命具有很高的可塑性
The stuff of life is so malleable
生命一旦出現  環境就開始
that once it got started, the environment molded it
將它塑造出驚人數量的不同形態
into a staggering variety of forms--
比我們所能展示的還多1萬倍
10,000 times more than we can possibly show here.
生物學家已經編錄了
Biologists have catalogued
50萬種不同的甲殼蟲
a half a million different kinds of beetles alone.
更別提那些數之不盡的細菌
Not to mention the numberless varieties of bacteria.
有幾百萬種不同種類的
There are many millions of living species
動物和植物  其中大部分依然未知
of animals and plants,  most of them still unknown to science.
這麼說吧  我們至今還沒有見過
Think of that-- we have yet to make contact
大部分的陸棲生物
with most of the forms of terrestrial life.
我們這個小小星球上就是有這麼多種的生命
That's how many kinds of life there are on this tiny planet alone.
生命之樹將觸角伸向所有的方向
The Tree of Life extends its feelers in all directions,
探尋可行的辦法
finding and exploiting what works,
為新的生命形式創造新的環境和機會
creating new environments and opportunities for new forms.
生命之樹已經35億歲了
The Tree of Life is three and a half billion years old.
時間已經長的可以發展出
That's plenty of time to develop
所有令人驚奇的本領
an impressive repertoire of tricks.
進化可以使一種動物
Evolution can disguise an animal
偽裝成植物
as a plant...
花費了數千代的努力
...taking thousands of generations
去設計一套精心製作的服飾
to contrive an elaborate costume
用來欺騙捕食者的眼睛
that fools predators into looking elsewhere for someone to eat.
或者植物偽裝成動物的模樣
Or it can disguise a plant as an animal,
花朵進化出黃蜂般的外表
evolving blossoms that take on the appearance of a wasp--
蘭花就用這種方式誘使黃蜂為他授粉
the orchid's way of fooling real wasps into pollinating it.
這就是強大的
This is the awesome
自然選擇下的變形本領
shape-shifting power of natural selection.
在密集雜亂的巨大生命之樹上
Among the dense, tangled limbs of the vast Tree of Life...
你在這裏
you are here.
數不勝數的眾多分支中的一小支
One tiny branch among countless millions.
科學揭示了所有生命本是同源
Science reveals that all life on Earth is one.
達爾文發現真正的進化機制
Darwin discovered the actual mechanisof evolution.
過去普遍的觀點是
The prevailing belief was that the complexity
種類繁多的生命必然是有造物主創造的
and variety of life must be the work of an intelligent designer,
分別創造了幾百萬種不同的生物
who created each of these millions of different species separately.
它認為 生物實在是太複雜了
Living things are just too intricate, it was said,
不可能由未經引導的進化而來
to be the result of unguided evolution.
就像人的眼睛
Consider the human eye,
一個極其複雜的傑作
a masterpiece of complexity.
要有角膜
It requires a cornea,
虹膜 晶狀體 視網膜
iris, lens, retina,
視神經 肌肉群
optic nerves, muscles,
再配合大腦複製的神經網絡
let alone the brain's elaborate neural network
才能產生一幅圖像
to interpret images.
它遠比其他任何一個人類製造的
It's more complicated than any device
物體要來的複雜
ever crafted by human intelligence.
所以 結論是
Therefore, it was argued,
人眼不可能是無意識的
the human eye can't be the result
進化產物
of mindless evolution.
要瞭解真相 我們需要回到
To know if that's true, we need to travel across time
我們有能力看之前
to a world before there were eyes to see.
最初 所有生物都看不見任何東西
In the beginning, life was blind.
這是我們的世界 40億年前的樣子
This is what our world looked like four billion years ago,
那時 生物還無法產生視覺
before there were any eyes to see.
直到幾億年過去
Until a few hundred million years passed,
突然有一天
and then, one day,
一個細菌的DNA產生了
there was a microscopic copying error
細微的複製錯誤
in the DNA of a bacterium.
這個隨機的突變給了這個微生物
This random mutation gave that microbe
一個可以吸收陽光的蛋白質分子
a protein molecule that absorbed sunlight.
想知道感光細菌的世界
Want to know what the world looked like
是什麼樣子的嗎
to a light-sensitive bacterium?
看看屏幕的右邊
Take a look at the right side of the screen.
突變繼續隨機的發生
Mutations continued to occur at random,
在其他所有的生物身上
as they always do in any population of living things.
另一個突變
Another mutation
使得細菌可以逃離強烈的陽光
caused a dark bacterium to flee intense light.
發生了什麼事
What is going on here?
黑夜和白晝
Night and day.
這些可以區分亮光的細菌
Those bacteria that could tell light from dark
相對其他細菌有了一個決定性的優勢
had a decisive advantage over the ones that couldn't.
為什麼
Why?
因為日光帶著強烈的紫外線會損傷DNA
Because the daytime brought harsh, ultraviolet light that damages DNA.
敏感的細菌避開強烈的光線
The sensitive bacteria fled the intense light
在暗處安全的交換
to safely exchange their DNA in the dark.
他們比其他生活在表面的細菌
They survived in greater numbers
更多的存活下來
than the bacteria that stayed at the surface.
日積月累 這些光敏蛋白質
Over time, those light-sensitive proteins
在更高級的單細胞生物身上
became concentrated in a pigment spot
濃縮成一個色素點
on the more advanced, one-celled organism.
這使尋找光亮成為可能
This made it possible to find the light,
對於需要陽光合成食物的
an overwhelming advantage
生命體來說 這是個壓倒性的優勢
for an organism that harvests sunlight to make food.
這是扁平蟲眼中的世界
Here's a flatworm's-eye view of the world.
這個多細胞生物
This multi-celled organism
在色素點中進化出一個小坑
evolved a dimple in the pigment spot.
碗狀的凹痕
The bowl-shaped depression
使動物可以區別明暗
allowed the animal to distinguish light from shadow
大致看出周圍的物體
to crudely make out objects in its vicinity,
包括食物和天敵
including those to eat and those that might eat it...
非常了不起的優勢
a tremendous advantage.
隨後 影像更清晰了
Later, things became a little clearer.
小坑變深了
The dimple deepened
進化成一個有開口的凹槽
and evolved into a socket with a small opening.
經過幾千代
Over thousands of generations,
自然選擇逐漸塑造出眼睛
natural selection was slowly sculpting the eye.
開放的地方凝聚成一個小孔
The opening contracted to a pinhole covered
由一層保護性的透明薄膜覆蓋
by a protective transparent membrane.
只允許一點點的光線透過小孔
Only a little light could enter the tiny hole,
但也足夠在敏感的眼睛內部表面
but it was enough to paint a dim image
描繪出一幅模糊的圖像
on the sensitive inner surface of the eye.
這演變出了聚焦
This sharpened the focus.
更大的孔可以讓更多的光線通過
A larger opening would have let in more light
產生更亮的圖像  但卻失去了焦點
to make a brighter image but one that was out of focus.
這個新形態引發了
This development launched the visual equivalent
視覺的軍備競賽
of an arms race.
競爭者們需要跟上才能生存
The competition needed to keep up to survive.
一個新的絕妙特徵出現了
But then a splendid new feature of the eye evolved,
可以同時保證亮度和清晰焦點的晶狀體
a lens that provided both brightness and sharp focus.
在遠古的魚類眼中
In the eyes of primitive fish,
小孔附近的透明膠體形成了晶狀體
the transparent gel near the pinhole formed into a lens.
同時 小孔擴大了
At the same time, the pinhole enlarged
允許更多的光線通過
to let in more and more light.
魚的視界高清了
Fish could now see in high-def,
不論遠近
both close up and far away.
然而 可怕的事情發生了
And then something terrible happened.
你注意到一杯水中的吸管
Have you ever noticed that a straw in a glass of water
看上去在水面處是彎的嗎
looks bent at the surface of the water?
那是因為光線從一個介質進入另一個介質時發生了折射
That's because light bends when it goes from one medium
就像從水到空氣
to another, say from water to air.
我們的眼睛最初是為了在水中視物
Our eyes originally evolved to see in water.
眼中的水狀液體巧妙地
The watery fluid in those eyes neatly
消除了折射的影響
eliminated the distortion of that bending effect.
但是對於陸地動物
But for land animals,
在空氣中成像的光線
the light carries images from dry air
進入他們濕潤的眼睛
into their still-watery eyes.
光線發生折射
That bends the light rays,
造成全面的失真
causing all kinds of distortions.
當我們的兩棲祖先從水中登陸時
When our amphibious ancestors left the water for the land,
原本在水中精確視物的眼睛
their eyes, exquisitely evolved to see in water,
卻在空氣中一塌糊塗
were lousy for seeing in the air.
從那時起我們的視力一直不好
Our vision has never been as good since.
我們一直認為我們的眼睛是最高級的
We like to think of our eyes as state-of-the-art,
但直到3.75億年後
but 375 million years later,
我們依然無法看清近在眼前的東西
we still can't see things right in front of our noses
或者像魚那樣在昏暗環境中
or discern fine details in near darkness
能夠辨別細節
the way fish can.
當我們離開水裏時
When we left the water,
為什麼大自然不能從新來過
why didn't nature just start over again
進化出一對新的眼睛
and evolve us a new set of eyes
可以在空氣中清晰視物
that were optimal for seeing in the air?
大自然並不是這樣的
Nature doesn't work that way.
進化過程對於已有的結構的改變
Evolution reshapes existing structures over generations,
是世世代代的慢慢適應
adapting them with small changes.
而不可能一切都
It can't just go back to the drawing board
推倒重來
and start from scratch.
進化中眼睛 在每一步的發展中
At every stage of its development, the evolving eye
都為我們的生存提供了極大的優勢
functioned well enough to provide a selective advantage for survival.
在現在存活的動物身上 我們發現了
And among animals alive today, we find eyes
各個發展階段的眼睛
at all these stages of development.
他們都很實用
And all of them function.
人類眼睛的複雜程度對進化過程來說
The complexity of the human eye poses
沒有絲毫難度
no challenge to evolution by natural selection.
事實上 沒有進化就根本無法解釋眼睛和其他生物學
In fact, the eye and all of biology makes no sense without evolution.
有人說進化論只是一種理論
Some claim that evolution is just a theory,
只不過是一種觀點
as if it were merely an opinion.
進化論就和萬有引力定律一樣
The theory of evolution, like the theory of gravity,
是科學的事實
is a scientific fact.
進化確有其事
Evolution really happened.
承認我們和其他生物出自同源
Accepting our kinship with all life on Earth
並不只是嚴謹的科學
is not only solid science.
在我看來 這也是一種崇高的心靈體驗
In my view, it's also a soaring spiritual experience.
因為進化是盲目地
Because evolution is blind,
它無法預測或改變悲劇的發生
it cannot anticipate or adapt to catastrophic events.
生命之樹有一些斷裂的分支
The Tree of Life has some broken branches.
其中大部分發生在
Many of them were severed in the five greatest catastrophes
五次最大的災難中
that life has ever known.
某個地方 有著一座紀念堂
Somewhere, there's a memorial
紀念著消失的物種
to the multitude of lost species,
滅絕物種的紀念堂
the Halls of Extinction.
隨我來
Come with me.
滅絕紀念堂
歡迎來到滅絕紀念堂
Welcome to the Halls of Extinction.
紀念著生命之樹上的斷枝
A monument to the broken branches of the Tree of Life.
對於依然存在的上百萬種生物來說
For every single one of the millions of species
可能上千種正在垂死掙扎
alive today, perhaps a thousand others have perished.
他們中大部分在與
Most of them died out in the everyday competition
其他生命形式的日常競爭中絕種
with other life-forms.
但也有很多是被地球上
But many of them were swept away in vast cataclysms
無法抗拒的大災難滅絕
that overwhelmed the planet.
在過去的5億年裏
In the last 500 million years,
發生過5次
this has happened five times.
奧陶紀(地質時代中顯生宙古生代的第二個紀)
5次滅絕地球生命的大災難
Five mass extinctions that devastated life on Earth.
泥盆紀(地質時代古生代中的第四個紀)
三疊紀(中生代的第一個紀)
最慘的一次發生在2.5億年前
The worst one of all happened some 250 million years ago,
白堊紀(地質年代中中生代的最後一個紀)
一個紀元的終結
at the end of an era
二疊紀(古生代的最後一個地質時代)
稱之 二疊紀
known as the Permian.
三葉蟲像裝甲部隊一樣
Trilobites were armored animals that hunted
成群結隊的在海床上肆虐
in great herds across the seafloor.
他們是第一批進化出
They were among the first animals to evolve
可以成像的眼睛的動物
image-forming eyes.
三葉蟲繁榮了大約2.7億年
Trilobites had a good long run, some 270 million years.
地球曾是三葉蟲的天下
Earth was once the planet of the trilobites.
但他們現在都沒了 絕種了
But now they're all gone, extinct.
他們中最後的一部分
The last of them were swept from life's stage
也隨著其他物種一起
along with countless other species
在空前的環境災難中絕種了
in an unparalleled environmental disaster.
大災難發生在今日西伯利亞的位置
The apocalypse began in what is now Siberia,
一場人類史上規模無比巨大
with volcanic eruptions on a scale unlike anything
的火山噴發
in human experience.
那時地球很不一樣
Earth was very different then,
只有一個超質大陸板塊和一片大洋
with one single supercontinent and one great ocean.
無情的滾燙的熔漿
Relentless floods of fiery lava
洪水般吞沒了比西歐還大的區域
engulfed an area larger than Western Europe.
斷斷續續的噴發持續了幾十萬年
The pulsing eruptions went on for hundreds of thousands of years.
融化的岩石
The molten rock
點燃了煤層 並且 污染了大氣
ignited coal deposits and polluted the air
充斥著二氧化碳和其他溫室氣體
with carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases.
地球溫度升高 洋流停止了流動
This heated the Earth and stopped the ocean currents from circulating.
有害的細菌迅速繁殖
Noxious bacteria bloomed,
海中其他生物幾乎全部滅絕
but nearly everything else in the seas died.
腐臭的水散發出致命的硫化氫氣體
The stagnant waters belched deadly hydrogen sulfide gas into the air,
導致大多數陸地生物窒息
which suffocated most of the land animals.
百分之九十的物種滅絕
Nine in ten of all species on the planet went extinct.
我們稱之為
We call it...
"大滅絕"
The Great Dying.
地球上的生命差一點全部絕種
Life on Earth came so near to being wiped out
需要花費上千萬年才能恢復
that it took more than ten million years to recover.
但是新的生命形式在慢慢進化
But new life-forms slowly evolved
開始填補由二疊紀大屠殺遺留的空缺
to fill the openings left by the Permian holocaust.
恐龍就是其中的大贏家
Among the biggest winners were the dinosaurs.
現在地球是他們的天下
Now the Earth was their planet.
他們的統治持續了1.5億年
Their reign continued for over 150 million years.
也是在一次大災難中
Until it, too, came crashing down
不可避免的土崩瓦解
in another mass extinction.
地球上的生命從太古時期就飽受摧殘
Life on Earth has taken quite a beating over the eons.
卻依然存在
And yet it's still there.
生命頑強得令人驚訝
The tenacity of life is mind-boggling.
我們總是能找到一條意想不到的生存之路
We keep finding it where no one thought it could be.
看到那條無名走廊嗎
That nameless corridor?
以後再說
That's for another day.
有種動物可以活在沸騰的水中或者堅固的冰層中
I know an animal that can live in boiling water or in solid ice.
可以10年不喝一滴水
It can go ten years without a drop of water.
可以不加防護的穿過寒冷真空
It can travel naked in the cold vacuum
並且充滿強烈輻射的太空 而毫髮無損
and intense radiation of space and will return unscathed.
節肢動物 又叫  緩步類動物
The tardigrade, or water bear.
生活在最高的高山還是最深的海溝
It's equally at home atop the tallest mountains
對他們來說沒有區別
and in the deepest trenches of the sea.
他們生活在苔蘚中  就在我們周圍
And in our own backyards, where they live among the moss
數也數不清
in countless numbers.
你可能從沒注意到他們
You've probably never noticed them
因為他們太小了
because they're so small.
差不多針尖大小
About the size of a pinpoint.
但他們很堅韌
But they're tough.
節肢動物在所有的5次大災難中倖存下來
The tardigrades have survived all five mass extinctions.
而他們則存在了5億年之久
They've been in business for a half a billion years.
我們一直認為生命很挑剔
We used to think that life was finicky,
他只能接受
that it would only take hold where it was
不太冷 不太熱
not too hot, not too cold,
不太暗 不咸 不酸 沒輻射 的地方
not too dark or salty or acidic or radioactive.
還有 不管怎麼樣 別忘了喝水
And whatever you do, don't forget to add water.
我們錯了
We were wrong.
節肢動物證明我們錯了
As the hardy tardigrade demonstrates,
生命可以承受人類絕對無法生存的環境
life can endure conditions that would mean certain death for us humans.
但是我們和那些生活在
But differences between us and life found
最極端環境下的生物
in even the most extreme environments on our planet
只有少許的區別
are only variations on a single theme,
就像一種語言中的不同方言
dialects of a single language.
地球生命的遺傳密碼
The genetic code of Earth life.
其他世界的生命又是什麼樣的呢
But what would life be like on other worlds?
有著完全不同歷史的世界
Worlds with a completely different history,
和我們完全不同的化學反應和進化過程
chemistry and evolution from our planet?
我想帶你去一個遙遠的世界
There's a distant world I want to take you to--
一個和我們這個截然不同的世界
a world far different from our own,
可能藏有生命
but one that may harbor life.
如果有 那絕對我們以前見過的
If it does, it promises to be unlike anything
大不相同
we've ever seen before.
雲霧完全包裹了泰坦的表面
Clouds and haze completely hide the surface of Titan,
即土衛六
土星的大月亮
Saturn's giant moon.
泰坦和地球有點像
Titan reminds me a little bit of home.
他也有主要以氮氣組成的大氣層
Like Earth, it has an atmosphere that's mostly nitrogen.
但是比我們的稠密4倍
But it's four times denser.
空氣中沒有絲毫氧氣
Titan's air has no oxygen at all.
比地球上任何地方都冷
And it's far colder than anywhere on Earth.
我依然想去那裏
But still... I want to go there.
我們必須下降
We have to descend
幾百公里的煙霧
through a couple hundred kilometers of smog
才能看到他的表面
before we can even see the surface.
但是下面藏著我們熟悉的風景
But hidden beneath lies a weirdly familiar landscape.
泰坦是太陽系中除地球外唯一一個會下雨的地方
Titan is the only other world in the solar system where it ever rains.
它有著河流和海岸線
It has rivers and coastlines.
有幾百個湖泊
Titan has hundreds of lakes.
有一個比北美的蘇必利爾湖還大
One of them larger than Lake Superior in North America.
蒸汽從湖面升起
Vapor rising from the lakes
凝結落下變成雨
condenses and falls again as rain.
就像地球一樣
The rain feeds rivers,
雨落進河流
which carve valleys into the landscape,
河流再將山谷雕刻出風景
just like on Earth.
但有一個很大不同
But with one big difference.
泰坦上 海和雨不是由甲烷和乙烷組成
On Titan, the seas and the rain
而不是水
are made not of water but of methane and ethane.
在地球上 這些分子組成天然氣
On Earth, those molecules form natural gas.
在寒冷的泰坦上
On frigid Titan,
他們是液態的
they're liquid.
泰坦上有很多水
Titan has lots of water,
但他們都凍的像石頭一樣硬
but all of it is frozen hard as rock.
事實上 這些風景和山脈
In fact, the landscape and mountains
都是水做的
are made mainly of water ice.
零下幾百度
At hundreds of degrees below zero,
泰坦寒冷得永遠不會有液態的水
Titan is far too cold for water to ever be liquid.
天體生物學家一直在猜想
Astrobiologists since Carl Sagan have wondered
泰坦上的碳氫化合物湖水中是否有生命
if life might swim in Titan's hydrocarbon lakes.
這種生命的化學成分
The chemical basis for such life
一定和我們所知的都不一樣
would have to be entirely different from anything we know.
所有的地球生命都需要水
All life on Earth depends on liquid water.
泰坦的表面沒有水
And Titan's surface has none of that.
但我們可以想像另一種生命
But we can imagine other kinds of life.
這種生物可能呼吸氫氣
There might be creatures that inhale hydrogen
而不是氧氣
instead of oxygen.
呼出甲烷 而不是二氧化碳
And exhale methane instead of carbon dioxide.
乙炔可能是他們的能量來源 而不是糖
They might use acetylene instead of sugar as an energy source.
我們怎樣才能找到他們
How could we find out if such creatures
如果他們的帝國躲藏在這石油般的海水下
rule a hidden empire beneath the oil-dark waves?
我們潛下克拉肯海
We're diving down deep into the Kraken Sea,
這是以北歐神話中的挪威海怪命名
named for the mythic Norse sea monster.
就算真有海怪在這裏
Even if there is one of those down there,
我們也看不到
we probably couldn't see it.
因為太黑了
It's so dark.
把地球上所有的石油和天然氣加起來
If you took all the oil and natural gas on Earth,
也只是泰坦儲量的極小一部分
it would amount to but a tiny fraction of Titan's reserves.
讓我們開點燈
Let's turn on some lights.
現在是表面下200米
We're now 200 meters beneath the surface.
看到什麼了嗎
Did you see something?
那邊 通道旁邊
Over there, by that vent.
也許我眼花了
Maybe it was just my imagination.
如果我們想要確切知道的話
I guess we'll have to come back
那麼我們就必須得再來一次
if we want to find out for sure.
我想和你再說最後一個故事
There's one last story I want to tell you.
這是最偉大的科學故事
And it's the greatest story science has ever told.
關於我們世界上的生命
It's the story of life on our world.
歡迎來到40億年前的地球
Welcome to the Earth of four billion years ago.
沒有生命的星球
This was our planet before life.
沒人知道生命如何誕生
Nobody knows how life got started.
撞擊和侵蝕摧毀了大部分的證據
Most of the evidence from that time was destroyed by impact and erosion.
科學處在無知和已知之間
Science works on the frontier between knowledge and ignorance.
我們不怕承認我們不知道
We're not afraid to admit what we don't know.
一點也不丟人
There's no shame in that.
丟人的是我們假裝已經有了答案
The only shame is to pretend that we have all the answers.
也許觀眾中有人
Maybe someone watching this
會成為首個解開這個謎題的人
will be the first to solve the mystery
關於地球生命的起源
of how life on Earth began.
從現存的微生物得來的證據顯示
The evidence from living microbes
他們最古老的祖先
suggest that their earliest ancestors
喜歡高溫
preferred high temperatures.
地球生命也許出現在熱水中
Life on Earth may have arisen in hot water
被水下的火山口環繞著
around submerged volcanic vents.
在卡爾·薩根的宇宙節目中
In Carl Sagan's original Cosmos series,
他找到了
he traced the unbroken thread that stretches
從將近40億年前的單細胞生物到你之間的
directly from the one-celled organisms
不間斷的線索
of nearly four billion years ago... to you.
相當於40秒的40億年
Four billion years in 40 seconds.
從不能分辨晝夜的生物
From creatures who had yet to discern day from night
到可以探索宇宙的生物
to beings who are exploring the cosmos.
這就是分子用40億年時間進化的結果
Those are some of the things that molecules do given four billion years of evolution.
中文字幕 @SaltyEggPain timhal
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息